Okay, so the success of the black civil
rights movement actually inspired other
marginalized Americans to fight for
expanded civil rights of their own and
it's about dang time we talked about it.
So if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. All right,
so the first group we need to consider
is the ladies. Yes, just like black
Americans, women have been fighting for
equal rights and social standing since
the country was founded. As you may
recall, Abigail Adams implored her
husband John to remember the ladies at
the constitutional convention and as it
turned out those sweaty delegates in
Philadelphia did not in fact remember
the ladies. And despite the fact that
women's rights activists scored a major
victory in 1920 with the ratification of
the 19th Amendment which recognized
women's right to vote, they still found
themselves on unequal social footing
with men. And what's more, women
actually played a vital role in World
War II and the civil rights movement and
yet they still lacked the political
power to change the issues that felt
particularly oppressive to them. But the
government responded to women's calls
for equal rights as they did to the
calls for black civil rights and like
the government's response to black civil
rights, those steps were ultimately
insufficient. For example, President
Kennedy formed the Commission on the
Status of Women which was tasked to
investigate gender inequality and make
recommendations for improving women's
status. And you can see a pattern here
with executive action in response to
calls for the expansion of civil rights.
So recall that Harry Truman responded to
growing complaints of inequality
experienced by black Americans by
forming the Committee on Civil Rights
which served the very same function as
the Commission on the Status of Women,
investigate and make policy
recommendations. And while both groups
found plenty of examples of inequality
and made bold policy recommendations
that aimed to correct them,
congressional resistance blocked or
diluted the full realization of equality
for both of these groups as was their
custom. Even so, the findings of the
committee brought the conversation on
gender equality front and center in the
American public square and therefore
laid the foundations for women to
achieve more gains over the next decade.
But one piece of legislation that
resulted from the committee's work was
the Equal Pay Act of 1963 which required
employers to offer equal pay for equal
work regardless of gender. So you know,
that's nice. But all that is just a
setup for the women's rights movement to
gather a full head of steam in the 1960
with the rise of second wave feminism.
Now I don't know much about anything,
but I do know that if there's a second
wave, there had to have been a first
wave, and as it turns out, I'm right.
Yes, the first wave of feminism had its
most focal moment in 1848 at the Seneca
Falls Convention, which hopefully you'll
remember was a gathering dedicated to
securing women's right to vote. And much
of the energy of the first wave of
feminism through 1920 was dedicated to
that singular task. But, then starting
in 1963, the second-wave feminist
movement got its ideological oomph from
Betty Friedan's book The Feminine
Mystique. And in the book, she argued
that many American women felt that their
assigned gender roles as wives and
homemakers and bearers of children left
many of them feeling isolated and
burdened and stifled in their true
potential. In other words, not every
woman felt that deep down warm tingles
when their entire lives were dedicated
to wiping baby butts and making their
husband sandwiches. Instead, Friedan
argued American society needed a change
in order to facilitate women's higher
education and contribution to the
workforce. And then add to that, the
birth control pill was introduced in
1960, which gave women far more control
over their reproductive health and
decisions. And apparently no small
amount of American women agreed because
Friedan's book sold widely, and with
that momentum, she joined other women's
rights activists to form the National
Organization for Women in order to more
formally work for women's equality in
American society. For example, after the
passage of the Civil Rights Act of 1964,
NOW lobbied the federal government to
more stringently enforce the law's
provision for gender equality in
employment. Additionally, NOW members
moved to add an Equal Rights Amendment
to the Constitution, which will protect
women's rights. And look, this amendment
was actually introduced way back in the
1920s, but it wasn't until the '70s that
it gained enough support to become a
viable option. But, you didn't think the
expansion of women's rights wasn't going
to be opposed, did you? Don't be crazy.
No, their work, just like other calls
for expanded rights, met with
substantial resistance. For example, a
fiery conservative woman named Phyllis
Schlafly formed an organization called
Stop ERA, which worked to prevent the
ratification of the ERA. And that's
because by Schlafly's reckoning,
feminism was a threat to more
traditional women who joyfully embraced
their roles as wives and mothers and
homemakers. Additionally, Schlafly and
her supporters worried that equal rights
for women could mean losing certain
benefits, not least exemptions for
military service. And in large part
because of Schlafly's efforts, the Equal
Rights Amendment fell three states short
of ratification. However, other feminist
groups believed that organizations like
now did not go far enough and instead
launched attacks against the social
system that they believed was
responsible for women's subordination,
namely the patriarchy. And by their
reckoning, only by dismantling the
persistent web of male domination could
women truly enter their full glory as
free women. To that end, women's
liberation groups protested the Miss
America pageant in 19 68, which they
viewed as a glaring example of the
objectification of women for the
pleasure of ogling patriarchal goons.
And to make their point, the
demonstrators put a freedom trash can in
their midst and threw away all the
trappings of female subordination like
bras and makeup and hairspray and all
the rest. However, the broader feminist
movement remained dedicated to making
sweeping changes that bolstered the
freedom and equality of women and to
that end they won a significant victory
in a 1973 Supreme Court case, Roe v.
Wade. This decision effectively made the
right to abortion unlimited in the first
three months of a pregnancy based on an
implied right to privacy in the 14th
Amendment. And feminists cheered this
decision as an important step in
acknowledging that they have the right
to make decisions regarding their own
bodies, although as we'll see in another
video, conservatives would mount a
significant opposition to this decision
in the coming years. And here's where I
tell you that those conservative efforts
ultimately led to the overturning of the
Roe decision in 2022, which effectively
returned the abortion question to the
states. Okay, now in addition to women,
Americans of Latin descent were also
emboldened to pursue greater access to
civil rights in the 1960s. And to be
clear, the Spanish-speaking population
of the United States was a diverse group
made up of many different nationalities,
but as a group they suffered many of the
same generalized inequalities. So, for
example, in the 1950s, Mexican farmers
in California organized themselves under
the leadership of Cesar Chavez in order
to gain the right to form unions and
negotiate for better wages. And by 1965,
Chavez and other activists formed the
National Farm Worker Association, which
organized a strike against California's
grape farmers that lasted for five
years. And eventually, the strike gained
national attention and support from many
American consumers who joined the
boycott by refusing to buy non-union
grapes. And by the end, Chavez and his
union secured many of the benefits that
they had so long fought for. And while
Chavez made use of non-violent tactics
to secure benefits for Mexican farmers,
other groups like the Chicanos advocated
for a more militant approach to
equality. So, influenced by the rhetoric
of Malcolm X and the Black Panthers,
Chicanos formed the Brown Berets in
which they promoted pride in their own
cultural identity while also arming
themselves for self-defense. All right,
now let's turn the corner and sit for a
spell with the American Indians and
their movement for greater access to
civil rights. American Indian movement
was formed in 1968 in response to the
disproportionate marginalization and
poverty experienced by American Indians
who had been consigned by the federal
government to live on reservations. And
hopefully you'll remember that pushing
American Indians to live on federally
designated reservations had a long
history. It began in earnest with Andrew
Jackson's support of the Indian Removal
Act in 1830 and then just kept moving
right along through the 19th century
with further constrictions on land
inequality with the Dawes Act in 1887. I
could go on. The point is American
Indians had fistfuls of receipts to
document their ongoing marginalization
at the hands of the American government.
And so, the goals of the American Indian
movement were to reclaim the heritage
and tribal traditions that had been lost
to American acculturation, achieve
self-determination, and address the
systemic poverty shared by many American
Indians. Additionally, this movement
formed in the immediate aftermath of new
laws that, you know, encouraged the
assimilation of American Indians, which
would of course weaken their tribal
associations. And one of the key events
of this movement was the occupation of
Alcatraz Island. So, as you probably
know, Alcatraz is home to a very famous
American federal prison. But, by the
1960s it had basically been abandoned
and according to an earlier treaty with
the federal government, any abandoned
land would be returned to the original
American Indian inhabitants. And so, in
1968 several dozen activists occupied
Alcatraz Island and claimed it for their
own. The occupation lasted for 19 months
and it ended after the federal
government made it pretty hard for the
Indians to continue living there. But
even so, it became a symbolic
cornerstone for American Indian
activism, which eventually led to the
Self-Determination Act of 1975, which
gave American Indians much greater
control over their lands and their
education and their law enforcement. All
right, now let's talk about how Asian
Americans joined the expansion of civil
rights party during this time. And for
this movement, let me introduce you to
an Asian American graduate student named
Emma Gee. So, she argued that the
national conversation on racial equality
was entirely framed in terms of black
and white and thus entirely ignored the
inequalities faced by all Americans of
Asian descent. And like American
Indians, Asian Americans also had metric
buttloads of receipts. There was the
Chinese Exclusion Act, there was
Japanese internment during World War II.
I could go on. And so, in response, Gee
created the Asian American Political
Alliance to work for the expansion of
Asian American civil rights. And of note
here, Gee popularized the term Asian
American as a way to encourage Americans
of various Asian ethnic backgrounds like
Chinese and Japanese, Filipino, Korean,
et cetera to pursue their goals by means
of a shared political identity rather
than remaining divided by national
origin. Therefore, the movement demanded
an end to Asian racial stereotyping and
greater political representation and an
expansion of ethnic studies in college
programs which at that point were highly
Eurocentric. that last point, in 1968,
Asian American demonstrators joined with
multiple ethnic protest groups to stage
the San Francisco State Strike. And it
called for universities to embrace a
wider cultural perspective in their
curricula. And this strike was
foundational in pressuring colleges to
include various ethnic studies tracks in
their programs. And then finally, the
LGBTQ+ community also experienced social
and political marginalization and sought
a more fullsome recognition and
protection of their civil rights.
However, since sexual orientation is not
visibly represented by skin color as
were other groups calling for equal
rights, their marginalization was often
more invisible to the wider world.
However, in 1969, the gay rights
movement made itself entirely visible in
the Stonewall Uprising. Now, the
Stonewall Inn was a gay bar in New York
City and because homosexuality was
illegal, police often raided this bar
and others like it looking for gay
people to arrest. And for the most part,
the people who gathered in these spaces
accepted this risk and tried their best
to stay under the radar. However, in
June of 1969, the Stonewall Uprising,
inspired by the wider cultural movement
for the expansion of civil rights,
changed all of that. So, when the police
raided the Stonewall Inn looking for gay
men to arrest, The bar's patrons
resisted and fought back. And that
resistance led to multiple organized
protests for the expansion of gay
rights, and activists encouraged gay
Americans to be open about their
identity and start working for the end
of discriminatory practices against the
community. And to that end, they created
the Gay Liberation Front, which promoted
gay pride and worked for equality in
American society regardless of sexual
orientation. And although their
victories would come slowly, the efforts
of gay rights activists pressured many
state governments to decriminalize
homosexuality over the course of the
rest of the 20th century. You can click
here to watch all my other Unit 8
videos, or you can click here to grab my
A Push Heimler Review Guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. I'm glad you came around, and
I'll catch on the flip flop. Heimler
out.